First
item is the roll call and seating of alternates.
I see Ann is here, Leanne is here,
Scott is here,
I'm here,
And
Susan is here. So we will seat Susan as the fifth member
of the Commission tonight.
Moving on to item three would be any additions or changes to the agenda.
Jim, did you have any changes
you wanted to make on that?
>> Yeah.
Can you hear me? Yep.
There should have been a memo that went out from
the
finance office
regarding the release of any
unspent funds under the
legal line item for planning and zoning for
this fiscal year?
Yes, I saw that.
>> Okay.
That would require
action I believe by the Commission. Okay.
>> So we will
add that under
item nine, the miscellaneous items.
We'll discuss turning money back in.
Now one of the things I forgot to ask
Amanda before we started, are you doing the minutes tonight? I did not see Linda
on here.
>> I'm here Jed. Oh, okay. I didn't see your name showing up there. Thank you, Linda.
>> Jed, if you try to go to the grid view, you can see everyone.
Try on your top right. Yeah. Well, let's.
>> Okay there we go yep
that
Perfect. Everybody wants how nice that is.
>> Who the
the name of the person is owner?
Do we know the other person on the call?
Just double checking.
Carry on. Okay.
>> One other minor change to the agenda on
item eight,
approval of meeting minutes, it says April 23,
I think
the date of the last meeting was April 20.
So with that, no other changes to the agenda.
Is
anybody from the public here and that would probably be owner, whoever that is,
Is there any public speak?
And Bill, we'll talk about your
you have got the main item tonight so you don't have to talk about that here. You'll get plenty of time in just a minute. Excellent.
Thank you.
>> Okay, hearing nobody that wants to speak on behalf of the public, we'll go on to
the new business.
And Bill, that's
yours
to
brief us on however you'd like.
We're ready to accept
the application
and
I did see Jim that
the
application form showed up in the file late this afternoon so we did
get that
on top of the numerous other documents that you sent to us Mr. Devine.
I'm Bill.
Very good, Bill. Don't need the mister.
>> Just for the record,
is Jim.
The application
was in fact submitted
prior to today.
>> Yep, I understand. We're just trying to Got lost in the abusive
computer.
>> I'm happy that we found it and got it posted before the meeting started tonight so that
when we get to you, Jim, you can tell us the status of having a complete application and we'll go
there from that. But heading back to Bill at this point.
Quick overview, Mr. Chairman.
>> I'm not hearing you as well as I was before, Bill. Well,
>> let's see if I can I'm on speakerphone. I'm hearing you better now, yep. Okay. I'll just hold this up. You want me to give you a brief overview of what we're Yes, please.
Okay.
I got to back up a little bit and tell you that this is our tenth house.
Did not expect to have a tenth, expected to stay in our ninth, which was a 1769
Georgian in Bosco in New Hampshire. We spent nine years restoring.
One quick sentence about that, the people who bought it had an appraisal and the appraisal report that it was
built in 1769,
but the effective age was eight years.
Think about that for a second. 1769
house effectively
eight years old. That's how much restoration we did.
So why are
we before the commission tonight and what motivated it and what's the plan?
Well,
the plan is that
we have a 51 year old son,
graduate of the College of the Atlantic in Bar Harbor, Maine. Jason has
never borrowed a dime in his life. He paid cash for everything he's ever done. He
wants to get out of the city of Baltimore.
He worked for us at one point in time back in the early 2000s
as a shipping manager for our catalog company.
And he wants to get into organic farming.
And we saw an opportunity to do a number of things,
one of which was to have him closer to us
and at middle 70s as my wife and I are. We
figured we were going need a little bit of help
eventually,
not today, but eventually.
Our daughter is in Portland, Oregon.
Jason wanted to farm, wanted to get
of Baltimore City and
we said, okay, let's look for a place.
We are Casey,
my wife and I are very much dyed in the wool and native New Englanders. We will not live anywhere else. We've looked at other states, we've lived in other states, Missouri, Illinois,
New York, Rhode Island,
Maine, New Hampshire and now Connecticut.
Connecticut, we wanted to come someplace where it was a little warmer, someplace that had another old house because we are hold house people.
And you can't go any further south in
New England than Connecticut.
So that was part of the reason for looking at Connecticut.
The other was looking for a property
that had an old house that we could
do what we do best with and that's restored,
that had enough room for our son to be able to start
a career as an organic farmer.
And we needed a place that either had an existing
accessory apartment, second building or one which had enough space and a town that was willing to let us do it. When we bought this house
back in the fall, we closed December 4 and
one of the three contingencies that we had when we bought them, when we made the offer on the house was the ability to build
what we were calling at that point in time a caretaker cottage and we still think of it that way.
We met with Jim's predecessor
the last week that John was here. He walked through it, told us, yes, you can do it. It's a lengthy process, plan on two to three months,
but you can do it.
Warned me that the application was going to be a pain in the neck.
So with that we removed the contingency.
The other two that we had incidentally had to do with septic and weld. We didn't care about the house. We've done this enough time that we could go through it and we knew the kind of stuff we were going to have to do to make this
restoration something we would be comfortable with.
So with all of that,
we chose Andover very carefully. We spent more than nine months looking for a property.
And
in fact,
when we came to look at this, we had a full price cash offer on our house in New Hampshire that we didn't sign off on because we didn't have a house yet.
And we looked at this one and one in Hebron as a matter of fact, the last two. And if this house had not been right for us, we would not have
made the move until
probably now sometime.
So that's
the background.
Our son is
ready and eager to come.
We're waiting for this crazy virus malarkey to go away
or at least enough so that we can get him up here. We're planning now sometime in mid to latter part of June.
If all goes well,
if the members members
of the commission
agree that we have a project that is worthy of being done in Andover, Connecticut.
We hope to be able to break ground in early July
and have him in his
detached accessory apartment to us, Caretaker's Cottage
by early fall.
Obviously no farming work until next year.
That's the overview. I do want to say before we get into what questions you may have,
I really want to thank you, Mr. Chairman and the members of the Commission and especially Jim
for
being
open to allowing me to try to put together
an application
that seemed to me at least to answer all of your questions and concerns
without having to go to that ungodly expense of doing some of the things that for a good reason are in the
site requirements of the zoning regulation.
I'm ready for your questions.
>> Well, I would hope that when we get to the end of this
process that
you would conclude that it was one,
not overly lengthy
and two,
not overly a pain in the neck.
So
I
am going to jump to Jim for his
assessment of the completion
of your application.
But
it looked like you did a lot of good work preparing for what you sent to us and we
all appreciate that.
Thank you. Jim,
>> what's your conclusion
after reviewing the materials that have been submitted?
>> Okay, I met with Bill
number of times over the course of the last few months and
spoken to him and I did visit the site briefly.
He put together
very
thorough application.
Neat.
As some of you know,
the application is coming for
you. This is the first
time anybody has applied for a special permit for a detached
accessory apartment.
This is the revision
4Point113
allows that under certain parameters.
It seems to have met those.
I believe we're still waiting for
final
approval on this septic. Is that accurate, Bill?
I'm sorry. Still waiting for what, Jim?
Yes.
An approval on the septic plan?
>> The other improvements?
Approval.
Oh,
the approval. Oh, yes. Well, no, I think the only other approval that is out there that I'm aware of at least is the wetland certificate,
As I've
shown you and done, and we've talked about this,
the wetlands are Okay, in
>> I'll touch base on that.
Currently,
I am not authorized
to sign off as wetlands agent.
Trying to work through that.
What I've done on other properties is
look at information that's available
in recent subdivisions.
Nothing on file for this particular property. I
did walk it,
both site is
well over a 100 feet from what appears to be wetlands in my opinion. I say well over maybe 125
feet.
That's about right. Site itself is
a fairly large lot and it's
fairly flat or at least a good portion of it is.
It seems to lend itself to the
bill's
intent here.
Just as a point of record, the application came in under the name of William and Casey Devine
Family Trust.
There's not any other name out there
associated with application, was my error.
At such time as
did the commission
choose to accept the application, that's the name that it came in under.
That's about all I have.
I still am continuing
to look at it, but it looks very thorough.
>> Okay.
Would any of the other
commission members have any questions
for the applicant here this evening?
>> What exactly
are we gonna go over tonight? I mean
b
is a long list of things that
that have to be put on a print.
>> And that's
a question that I would put
back to Jim. I'm a little
not certain myself when we're talking about an accessory apartment.
Do all the requirements of a site plan
need to be
complied with as you go through the special permitting thing? It says
>> in 4 Eleven-two,
which
is the accessory apartment that it tells
you to go back to 232 B.
And 232 B is, you know, there's 10 or 12 things that are missing.
>> That that is absolutely correct, mister Person. That
section 23.2 B, the
site preparation thing,
as I mentioned I guess when we first talked at the last meeting and when I had numerous discussions with
both
Jim and his predecessor
that,
you know, I'm an old dude and I've done a lot of stuff in my life
from writing
major grant applications to owning and running radio stations.
And I got to tell you in my 74,
I never panicked over anything in my life.
So I looked at that site plan requirement.
And it was when
I had the advice
that
and when I read the
section and I've forgotten what the proper number is,
where the zoning regulations
and I think in their wisdom when they were written
gave
the commission the opportunity to waive
any sections of that 20 three-2B
site requirement
that they felt could be waived.
And if I had to
hire someone to go 200 feet from my lot
to try to determine the height of people's houses, where the septics were, where the wells were.
If I had to do the
diameter of
all of the trees that were three feet at chest height and identify all the flowers and the fauna,
I couldn't have done it.
To
have someone who prepares these kinds of things do this would probably have cost us, I don't know, $40,056,000
dollars $7,000
and
at that point that would have made the project with our
budget that we have for this, which is I think a pretty significant one,
it would have made it inadequate.
So I guess, Ms. Person, the answer to your first comment is yes,
The actual regulations
do have a number of points in them that have not been addressed
by my application.
What I think my application
does do,
consistent
with the
zoning regulations as I've read them, I think they do
give you everything that you need
to do your due diligence to decide whether or not this application for a detached accessory apartment
meet
the spirit and the letter of the zoning regulations.
To be blunt, to be honest, I believe they do. But you are correct, sir. It it it does.
>> I I would say that what you're saying is accurate, but, you know, it clearly states
that all the things in twenty three two b
have to be met,
And it's not like it's a lot.
It's, you know, an A2
by a professional engineer,
you probably have to have the test bits where they're located on there,
the height and type of construction of the building,
building coverage on the property,
which is not a big deal,
the plan for the cars, where the cars are going to be located.
E and S,
that's a requirement 4.1.
To test, I know you had a water test done for,
I
don't know what if it was just for gallons per minute or the quality was done, but that has to be done. The approval by wetlands has to be done, lighting,
where the lighting's gonna be.
Mr. Devine, this is our first
accessory apartment and I think we need to do it
fairly
adequately.
And and all that stuff you know a surveyor
can put that on a piece of on a drawing
very quickly.
>> Sir, I do not disagree with you. You
need to be comfortable with this. I absolutely concur with that But
I think that the framers of
these sections
of the zoning regulations
recognized
that there were certain projects
that were much bigger
and certain projects that would be much smaller.
That's why I believe
that
the Commission was given the authority
to waive
any portions of Section 20 three(two) that
it
decided to.
As I went through
Sections
four, five, and six, I believe those are the
three ones that
I dealt with,
I don't know what to tell you, sir, but I guess I when
you talk about lighting, where does the lighting need to be? There isn't going to be any lighting.
There isn't going be any lighting.
There
are so many things
that are
by
our town zoning regulations permitted by special permit
that it's a huge shopping list,
huge shopping list.
And obviously if somebody wanted to build a I don't have the regulations in front of me. So I apologize if I'm
saying something that's way off base.
It's not a nursing home.
It's
a seven ninety two square foot
apartment.
That's what it is.
I don't have to worry about
access and parking and
how much is going to be permeated and all the kinds of things that someone building
or wanting to a special permit to build something
bigger would be. And
>> I concur with what you're saying, mister Devine. I'm only one of five.
You know, if other people
have views, know, everyone's
views should be brought up and I'm open to any,
any new information. I always am. I'd like to hear what everybody else has to say about it.
Thank you.
>> This is Jim. I just wanna note that that,
mister Devine did request waivers
in in this
randomly.
I mean, he did specifically
request waivers.
And
the way the process is structured, waivers are granted until such time as the application
is the
public hearing is open and the commission is deliberating.
So
that's
how we got where he is. Right.
>> I've heard of waivers being granted for scale
or
a two foot rule on the topography
or some stuff like that, you know, wetlands if there's
none in the vicinity.
All those things are
things that I
under
This
is building, mean if you're gonna put in a shed they have to have it on a piece of paper someplace.
With the building,
you know, style, what you're building it out of, know, everything has to be there. This is gonna be a dwelling.
Just think that there should be a little bit more information on a little bit more information given. That's all. That's all I'm saying. Scott,
>> he did provide a copy of the architectural plans. He provided a map that showed where this is gonna be located.
And so
I thought most of his waiver requests
were very reasonable considering 790
foot building.
But and I thought the architectural build design was very attractive and in keeping
with a historic site of this type.
>> Right and
I'm glad that you're saying that Sue, I'm happy that somebody else is saying something.
One thing that it does say is that it's supposed to be a professional
engineer
that
you know Connecticut
registered professional engineer that has to sign off on this.
If you want to waive that also that's fine with me too.
>> Oh I think we had the did you have an I can't I don't have up in front of me right now. I did study your plans this afternoon.
Were they done by an architect or an engineer?
>> The house plan was done by an architect.
Okay. The
the A2 survey of the lot, that was obviously done by a professional
surveyor.
>> Maps that he used were copies of an eight of
plans prepared by an engineer
for the best part of the subdivision years ago, I believe.
They were just reused.
>> And we've done that. We've allowed that repeatedly in the past take
plans that existed, older
A2 surveys and have gone with them. I
>> don't have any problem with that using that one. I think that you could,
you don't think that adding
an additional structure to an
existing state to by a professional engineer is
anything that you'd like to see?
>> On
the drawing for the caretaker's
cottage,
I see where it
looks like put it's up by an architect.
And so
if we go back
to the start, I agree with Bill, I agree with Scott,
I agree with Susan,
and I agree with Jim.
And so
as I look through
the information that Bill provided to us,
I thought that he hit most of the high points
on all the requirements
that I could find in there. As he mentioned, you know, at one point when we were looking at the
property,
and I forget the fellow's name where he's got the home business,
And one of the things we specifically looked at over there was the lighting around
the big garage that he was putting up for his
home business over there off of
Long Hill Road.
So there are some things in there that
are clearly not
applicable.
I tried to go through our checklist
to see
how did that do for getting
the things that we were looking for.
And
you know that checklist tries to be one thing, it tries to be
the answer to everybody's prayers on how to get ready for an application
and I wasn't really satisfied
with my walking
through that either.
And so
the way the process
should go
is that all the materials come in,
Jim and Bill would have sat down with the checklist, gone through item by item and
they can have a discussion and say yes, it's applicable and we got it. No, it's not applicable
and here's why.
And we need this one and it will be submitted before we get to the public hearing.
But the checklist wouldn't have done an item by item
look
like you did, Scott, when you were looking at that particular section there.
A couple of the things that I went through, you know, and it said
each special permit will have the
erosion and
sediment
plan. And I went back and I looked at Bill's notes that he provided.
And I thought he had
a satisfactory
discussion in there on
erosion and sediment controls.
And essentially, you don't need much to go do what he's looking to do.
So I guess
it would certainly be easier to do that if we weren't in an environment where we couldn't get a couple of us sitting around a table looking at a drawing
to do that. And I
was hoping that by now we would be back to the point where we could do that. We're not there yet.
What I kind of like to think the model should be,
would be that
when we do
something like an accessory department, and I agree this is the first time through it, we need to do a pretty close look, Or even the subdivision that we went through for the first time
a month ago with the open space issues.
That we have that discussion and we go item by item and
we say,
yep, this we need, this we don't, and
we can come up with a small list. But as I
went through
all the things in that section you cited, Scott, I was hard pressed to come up with something
that I thought was important
that he didn't include there.
But that doesn't mean we shouldn't be out there looking for it. That doesn't mean we shouldn't
figure out how
to have the special permit. The first special permit I went through my feedback to the group after we were done was it's a free for all. We didn't pay any attention to any of the requirements. We just went out and said, okay, go ahead.
And so
we are looking at going from one extreme to the other and trying to find what makes sense
going through there.
If any member of the Commission had, you know, I guess the other thing that I was thinking of as I went through here
was the question on topography and do we have a drawing that specifies
the topography of the land.
And
that concerned me a little bit with the development of a sediment erosion control plan.
But I heard the
comment either Bill or Jim made that it's fairly level.
And one of the suggestions that I was going to make here tonight
is that
ask if there's any interest in having the Commission go over and do a sidewalk on the property
because I think that would help us gain a better perception for
what are the important attributes that we need to make sure get included in the final plan.
Are we happy with the information you provided us there?
>> I'd be delighted to have you come look at the property.
>> So
how does the commission feel
about doing something like that?
>> Jed, this is Leanne. I have a couple of questions. Yes. Go ahead, Leanne.
Is
excuse me what paperwork has been submitted. I'm looking for attachments from last month and if anything was sent
today
or even since the last meeting regarding this, I didn't get it. I don't know if it's something came today that Susan is referring to.
I also, as you know, didn't get a copy of the meeting notice for tonight. So I don't know if something is not coming through to me. Are there drawings? Are there waiver requests
that others received?
Others on the commission? Okay. So Leanne,
>> if you
and I know Scott
and I had a conversation on that earlier today too.
If you go to the planning and zoning,
go to the town website, click on planning and zoning and then scroll down underneath all that introductory stuff,
you will find a
section
that has and it's right above the different applications that you could click on.
I think Amanda is trying to call up that screen
>> now maybe. So this is not the section with the It meeting
>> is not. No, and that was one of the things I was going to talk about later
is,
know,
Jim and I have been talking about what should we be talking about, and it's the process.
Because
how do we bake this stuff in a cogent form where it's easy
for us to find it? We
need to talk about why the emails
aren't getting through to the people that need them and that sort of thing. But
you see up on the screen now the Planning and Zoning Commission and I think
Amanda if you scroll down.
Yes.
>> So I just wanted to share that Leanne does have an AOL account
and it's not her,
it's us. Our town email has trouble getting through to AOL and Yahoo account.
Sometimes that happens.
>> I know reference, I do have a Gmail account that we can use, and I it's just been the last
mean, it's just been actually this month and if anything was sent, as I said, other pertaining to this application that we're talking about or something else that I didn't get since our last meeting because in the past I haven't had any trouble. But no, I haven't seen anything
regarding this application
at all.
>> So up on the screen now, Leanne, is
all the information that was submitted with respect to this application.
Okay.
>> And
there's a lot of it there and we're just
talking about accepting the application tonight.
But
there's a fair amount of information there. It might not be everything that's
in accordance with that section 23.2,
there's
a fair amount. And I went looking through something that troubled me that I couldn't find.
And as I say, I was struggling with the topography, but my suspicion was it was a fairly level lot. And that was
commented
on here tonight.
>> Okay, so if we're not finalizing anything tonight, we're just accepting, then I have time to go in or somebody has time to send these things to me to another email address.
>> You do. Just to go back to the point on
the email distribution,
we need to standardize how we want to do business. Sometimes
all the documents get emailed out to us.
For this case, it's all here in one spot.
And I think that's good.
Scott and I were talking earlier
about
for the Board of Selectmen, there's a folder for the meeting. Well, I think after I thought about that, I like the way that this is laid out here because
all the information on this particular
application
is in one spot, whether it came in the last meeting, this meeting,
or in preparation for the next meeting,
anything you want to see is right there.
I would share that I also did not get the email from the town.
Well, did get it.
Somehow every now and then one from the town goes into my spam file
and I don't get to see it. And so we'll look on
getting
the email
problem straightened out. But
I thought
we had a pretty good
documentation
justification
for what
Bill was looking to do.
If there's
I'm
like Scott said, I'm one vote.
But
I thought he did a pretty thorough job.
Certainly
neither Jim nor Bill know how to read my mind yet as to know exactly what I'm looking for.
But I thought he came pretty close to getting it there.
Don't want to give away the farm but I don't want to make it such a pain in the neck process that we can never get through it either.
So that's
kind of where my
feelings are on
the subject here. I want to have a good standard, but I don't want to make it
excruciating
where we're putting the same amount for a caretaker cottage that we would for building the Taj Mahal.
>> I mean even down to the Aspville.
What are you going to do for that?
>> Yes, the As Built, in fact, I don't know whether it's part of all of this or not, but I know I had discussions about it.
What I am willing to do, and again, I'm not sure that I put it anywhere in there, there has to be an As Built. It ought to be done by an engineer or by a surveyor
after the foundation is in.
And I
think that may be one thing that
you really want to see
plus to be honest if you look at the A2 survey
and you look at
the actual, what I call the location,
which is the aerial map, you can see that
the existing barn
is not positioned correctly on the A2.
So there really should be an as built,
which is done after the foundation at least is in maybe even beyond that. I don't know. That's up to you folks to tell me when you want it done. But there should be
an as built done.
I agree with that. If
>> you have an engineer come for that,
it would be very simple for him. If he's going to do the as built, he can put in a lot of stuff real quick. It doesn't take long for an engineer to
put a few different things in
so that we can see
that a lot of these things are on the print.
Yep.
>> And
in the, you know, the septic test holes. Where
are they located?
>> You have those. The the test holes are on the
the the testing locations.
>> Right. I I I read all that, Bill. But it's
normally just all on a print.
And he could put the cars where the parking is going to be where you it only takes those guys very,
very short period
of time to do that kind of stuff.
That's that's that's all I'm having a problem with is just, you know, something
documented,
more documentation
is all I'm looking for.
>> Can can that be done this person? I mean, after the foundation goes in?
>> Bring them there at one time and have them
fulfill all these requirements
and I,
you know, that's fine with me. But you had, I read through every document that you had and it all looked really good. But then when I go back to '23 to be
and it specifies
that they want these things.
And
that's all I'm having a problem with. The rest of it was fine. I think you did a great job.
You did a much better
than a lot of people I've seen.
>> Thank you. Honestly,
appreciate the comments and I really did did try my level best to answer all of this. There is some stuff that I could not do. There's some things that no
way I could do in any kind of reasonable timeframe,
like the topography stuff. I mean, looked at all the maps
and it was at that point when I looked at all the maps that I began to have a I
hate to admit this because I'm a pretty calm guy.
I had a panic attack and I looked at that 52 item checklist
and I went through it.
And just as
Chairman, as you said, I went through and I checked off all of the things and I wrote NA beside the things I didn't think
necessary
or at least from my perspective, I didn't.
And any engineer can overlay
photography on a map.
>> Well, I do agree that there should be an as built.
I guess my
questioning at this point
is
it's a kind of a rock and a hard place. I'm
willing to do it. That's not the question here. I'm just wondering whether or not
it provides the town with a more accurate, better record and provides this landowner
with a better record
if
the as built
is done
after the foundation is in place for the building.
I'm also waiting for the actual drawing
from DrainWorks
from Justin in terms of the septic stuff. I mean he's been here, he shot the
levels and
Thad King had told me where he thought the tank should be and where he thought
the leach field should be And of course, Justin has all of that. And when when Thad King was here, I actually used a couple of driveway stakes to mark
what he had suggested for the actual locations.
Then when Justin came and configured the whole thing, it's
>> And the engineer can put all that stuff on the document for you,
make a better
document.
>> Yeah, this is Jim. First
of all, I'd like to address Leanne's
question
earlier
and I apologize you didn't
get a copy of the
agenda which would have directed you to the town's website. But if you send me your email, I'd be happy to get it out. But there is one item that is not on here,
which Bill submitted,
which is the request for waiver.
And the reason it's not on here is because I didn't have it posted quick. Part of it is we just started doing this.
Wetlands commission for instance,
the
beauty of this is that it goes back. In wetlands a lot of times there's applications that
stay with them for three or four months.
And
folks have trouble going back and finding finding the right documents.
So this way they're together by, you know, they're lumped by application.
So so they're
like, if if the commission intends,
I mean, it sounds like they're looking for, well, at least some folks
are looking for additional information.
And I mean, this had come up, and
I'm wondering if sidewalk
is gonna transpire.
If I had a checklist in place at that time and got a better handle on exactly what
waivers
would be
entertained which just
wouldn't.
And if we could
that early on and try
to accommodate
the applicant here.
>> Again Jim, the model that I would like to go to is where you
and the applicant sit down ahead of time
using your best judgment and then you come
and brief the Commission on
these are the that we didn't think would be appropriate
for this application and here's why as opposed to us going out and hunting for which ones
weren't
being complied with.
>> Jim, what were the waivers anyways and what were the applicable
>> actions?
What
were the waivers and where were they located in '23 to be? I don't have the numbers. Don't have that. I
have that information. I'm sorry.
Well,
>> I can go upstairs to my office computer
and print something out, but I can't pull it up on Yeah, no, I think
again, if Amanda
Amanda can open it up and share it. The
third thing
well,
Oh, here's question.
>> Where you got your arrow.
Open that up. Yeah. There's
>> actually two different documents.
The one that Amanda is pulling up right now, the waiver request,
that was done back in March.
And I would admit
to being ignorant when I did it. I simply said, I want to waive the whole four, five and whatever it was.
And the more I looked and then I had discussions
with your zoning officer and it became obvious to me that
I
was not very intelligent when I simply did that blanket.
And I did a second document,
which Jim has and which I do have in my computer upstairs,
which walked through and specifically identified
which individual ones that I wanted
to do.
Well, actually, no. This may be,
yeah, actually I'm looking at this up on here now.
See I
said items four, five, and six all and that's ridiculous.
Okay? That's ridiculous.
>> Yes. And this is the letter we talked to last
month
and had that discussion.
Yes. And
>> I think at that point last month
I was a lot more clear
in terms of my concerns.
And in fact, as I recall, my discussion was, it seemed to make a lot of sense to be able to take the A2 and
do all of the basically to do the flight plan
on the A2
with such additional information
as would be necessary
to really give the commission
the information it needs to do the due diligence that I understand and appreciate you need to do.
>> Okay. So we're saying there's a document that requests more specifically
items to waiver than the one we're looking at on the screen right now? Is that true?
>> Yeah, I did. I did one.
Again, it's
I don't even remember now because
I went through. I mean for example,
the one I did back in March said all of Section four.
Well, mean Section four, I think Section one, two and three
are all basic information things that would have to be there. So there's no way that the commission is going to waive every single item under 20 three(two).
You have by
the regulations
the right to waive
anything you wish under 20 three(two).
What the
regulations
say you cannot waive
is so gee, I don't even have the numbers in front of me, but it was
the sections that I addressed in one of my notes
as a matter of fact.
>> Is there anything else that I should pull up right now that would be helpful? Any of these?
>> Well,
Amanda, I'm looking for
a
drawing and it's got number two eighty nine on it. It's page eight of 14.
And
that shows the little subdivision
over there, it looks like.
Jim, do you know which one that is?
>> Try
that location map, Amanda. That
be at there.
This
>> actually gives you, I think, a little bit of a sense about the levelness of the site.
Mr. Person, you raised a question at one point about that. And I think Mr. Chairman, you mentioned that you thought the lot was pretty level. That location one, which Amanda just pulled out before,
really shows I think how level that is. This
is the A2.
This is the survey
that I referenced
back in
the April meeting
about what I thought I would do. And what you have here,
you can see where the three arrows converge.
That's the location
of what I call a caretaker's cottage. Yes, right
there. That's it. The reason that there's a line there, there's the building and then there is a six foot porch and a six foot deck.
And then the arrows tell you how it's positioned relative to the property line for my abutters.
It doesn't show the distance, which is approximately three fifty nine feet from the back of that to the back of the property.
The
I tried to show the
yellow is the proposed septic system
to support the
caretakers cottage.
I have the existing house,
septic system marked in a rectangle down below to give you a sense where that might be.
And then the
arrows
in the driveway,
that was one of the things, this person that I think you mentioned.
There's an existing garage,
which also has a 10 foot addition to it,
which was done in March of this year with a proper building permit.
And what I have done, I've had Ron we had horrible, horrible bittersweet
and that area to the front side of the garage where there's
some, yeah right there. That was a mess. I mean there was a torn up doghouse in there. There was rubbish. There was the
tailgate of a pickup truck,
rubber tires,
bittersweet like crazy and
trees, but it was horrible, just horrible.
I had Ron come in and Ron
took his bobcat and cleared the whole thing out. It's not been
contoured quite yet. But my
hope and my expectation is that both construction vehicles
and if ultimately we decide we want him to be able to drive out to the house or whatever
is that we would use that access to the front of the garage and then go along the tree line, just on the grass.
And if that didn't work, then I have a second way which is between the septic system and the garage.
I prefer not to use that for a construction vehicle because it's a little too close to my lease field.
I prefer not to have a heavy duty vehicle like that. So anyway that
gives you a
pretty good sense of what we're looking at and where
the the the detached
accessory apartment,
the Divine Caretaker cottage
was was very, very carefully positioned.
>> Another thing,
Bill, is you you need to have the location of reserve septic area on a print.
>> I'm sorry. What do you mean by a reserve? The reserve area for that septic.
>> Eastern Highland must have
dug for the
reserve system area, right?
>> Okay. The reserve system, you mean the leach field? Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. The reserve area for the leach field?
Right.
Right. That's
usually located on a print also.
>> I don't know what a reserve is. I know that there's a tank and there is a leach field.
I said to Jim,
there is
as I've read all of the zoning regulations and I think I've read all of them very, very carefully as it applies to my project
that there was no requirement to have a septic design there. There was a requirement
to have a soil test,
which we do have.
I've gone a little bit further than that,
although I don't have the evidence for you because Justin didn't deliver it when he said he would.
And I emailed him today. By going further, I mean, I literally
have a design coming
with the specific locations for the septic system and the leach field.
>> And they must have dug a pit for the reserve because they don't do it without having
the reserve on.
They always have a reserve.
>> I'm
sorry. Don't I still don't I'd be happy to I'd
>> be happy to work with Bill
and address
checklist.
Go through twenty twenty three item by item
and come up with a recommendation
based on your comments this evening.
What
the commission
needs and what might be waived.
>> Appreciate that, Jim. And Scott, I appreciate I your
looked at this drawing and I said, well, that tells me what I need to know.
And I didn't have the experience to think now there's probably a couple other things in there
that we want to have with it.
So I guess my goals are now cut in two.
I know we can't make it so there's not a pain in the neck process.
The best we can do is make it timely.
But
Bill, is that
drawing that Scott's
alluding to something that you think you could have
done
within three weeks so that we can have it in place to support?
>> Number one, I don't
have a clue who I'm going to go to to have that done.
But I will find someone.
>> Bill, if you know where all your pins are or some of the pins?
Yes, sir. I know where all the pins are. I have to tell them. That's very helpful for them. All they have to do is set up those pins.
>> Is no be able to look for a surveyor to do this.
If it's a surveyor, there's no problem. I can find a surveyor.
Well, you're
not.
You're not really proposing any drainage.
No.
>> A piece, I don't believe would be necessary.
I think an LS would
would meet the other record regulations.
I believe. I can double check that.
>> Well, just just Jim, it just says professional
Connecticut
registered professional engineer.
Okay.
So it's gonna be Pete.
>> Ken,
I I
don't know how to say this other than than honestly and and and respectfully and and bluntly.
I am right now
very, very concerned
about
being delayed
another month.
Tried to start this process back in March.
Jim was working with me.
The virus stuff got in the way, so I did not have my
April meeting
in March as I had hoped to.
It has been my original hope to be able to break ground in June. I know I can't do that now. I
have no problem with the delay.
But if
you folks aren't comfortable setting
a public hearing date for
the June meeting,
I'm going to lose another month.
And if I lose another month, then I
mean, I'll live with whatever I have to live with.
I admit that.
But
gosh, it's going to make it difficult for me.
If there's any way
that
I mean, if
the public hearing is at the June meeting, that would be June 15.
If I back up ten days, if I can find
a Connecticut registered engineer
who can do the
as built I just want to be really clear that
we all know what it is you're asking me to do. So I don't come up with something wrong.
I really live in fear of additional delays right now.
That's not your problem. I know it's not your problem. I'm not trying to make it your problem.
I'm just trying
to be as open and as honest
as I can.
I guess
with what's
required for the timeframes and everything else,
is it possible
for you folks to
accept this application with a provision that an as built
be in the hands of the zoning officer
by a date certain and tell me the date,
so that the public hearing can be scheduled for June.
Otherwise, I'm going to lose a whole month.
Am I totally out of line?
>> I don't think you're totally out of line Bill. Then,
>> If you can get all these things I'm sorry. The Asbills
is after you put the before you start framing.
Soon as the cement's done, you put do the as built.
>> That's what I that that had been my plan, and that's that's what I wanted.
>> How are you gonna know where to dig the hole if you don't have a stake in the ground?
I do.
I've staked the house.
>> Well, if you staked it out, you know, the
surveyor can come over and and
locate those stakes on
a drawing. Yeah.
Very easily. All these things, all these stakeout things that you have, all they have to do is transfer
them to a drawing.
All you have to do is stand there to pick up a couple pins and then go
your stakes and put them on the print.
Okay.
>> That's all they have to do. And then you've got to fulfill these things and I think you can easily.
>> When you say
registered professional engineer,
is that also what I normally refer to as a surveyor?
>> Yeah, you can probably ask Jim Hartman at Allisi Hill.
He can point you in the right direction.
Okay, sorry. Will.
>> You have to have the reserve system on there. You have to have you know you should write down all those things in twenty three-two B.
It doesn't have the
EHHD
should have given you dug the holes for the reserve
they should tell you where the reserve will be and he can put that on there also.
This is a real live house it's not a shed.
Correct.
>> Okay.
So
kinda regrouping here.
I think there's
two issues.
The first of which would be
we need a motion to accept the application.
The second issue is do we want to do a site visit?
And I'm not really particular
about which order
we do those things, but I think
those are the two things that we have that
are the next steps.
Anybody have any comments on
>> that not being the way ahead here? What about the other the wetland review, Jim?
>> I was going to have Megan take care of it because
she
took the DEP course.
Yeah. She's signing off.
>> She can sign off if it's
it's
out of the area.
Do we also yes?
>> Think she still has to be designated by the commission when that can take place.
Yeah.
>> Actually,
I think what we have to do is we have to get some directives from.
My understanding is next
The time turning from Mark Brantz.
>> He's on the first side.
And we will leave that meeting with
an answer
to the wetlands.
Okay.
You know, there's
about three different ways that we can
get through that.
I don't think
to come to a finding that
the wetlands review doesn't need to take place
should take the lengthy process that it does if the wetlands review does have to take place.
If you go back to the Crogg diagram
and it
seems to have a pretty good
sense, I would think, a
stream
over
next property
over to them that's on the far side of that property and it's got wetlands around that.
There certainly was nothing
around Bill's property to do that. That's good. Yeah.
And so I think we can come through that whether it needs a whole board
decision that
it does not
need to be acted upon through wetlands where Megan does it herself.
That
>> will happen at June 1. Kind of be out of the 100 foot Trunk View area, doesn't it? Yes,
and it looked to me like it was.
>> What I can do is ask Megan to take a look at it prior to that June 1 meeting. No matter.
So it can be addressed.
No matter what.
What parameters there are?
Whether she needs Commission action or not.
I mean, she does.
She's not gonna.
All she might be looking for is designation,
not a.
Not enough.
>> Jim?
Yes. Is Megan taken training to become the Wetlands agent or you know to apply for it?
She took the training. Mean that's not her intent.
Okay.
>> But she she was able to take it quite frankly because she's a DEP employee.
Oh, she is. Okay. And she was able to do it sort of in house, I believe.
Okay. Or it's just not available right now.
>> Okay. I don't know her. I was just asking because we've you know, John left and then the other person left, and then,
you know, you had mentioned her taking the course right now. So I was just asking for
my and anyone else's information.
>> I think
we can come through the wetlands issues before we get to a public hearing.
So let's take the easy question first.
Is there a desire that we go do a site visit?
I think it would be helpful to me. Jim, I know you've already been out there.
>> I
don't have any problem with going out there I would like to go shave too.
>> Fine with me.
Yeah it's okay with me I've driven by it I've just never been on the property.
>> Yep.
Well,
Bill's already said he's got the location for the
house staked out and I think that
just the situational awareness of going out there and take a look would be helpful for all of us with understanding
what it is we're talking about. Okay.
So with that in mind, we normally
is Saturday morning convenient for
folks to go out and do it? And I know this is a holiday weekend
with all the social restrictions in place. I don't know that that makes an awful lot of difference.
If we were to do something like 09:00 on Saturday, would that work for
everybody?
That's fine. Does
that work for you, Bill?
>> I am happy to
have you folks here whenever it is most convenient for you. Okay.
>> Jim work for you?
Jim, does Saturday morning work for you?
Yes, it does. Okay,
very good.
>> Jed?
Yes. This is Leanne again.
Should we have the sidewalk before the public hearing?
>> Yes, we should.
In
fact, that's the way our procedure
has it be done.
>> Okay, because I think in the past we've done it both ways. Yep.
>> But I think the
more information we have before we go to a public hearing, the better the public hearing
will be.
>> I understand that part. And if you have a public hearing that is not continued,
then you don't have a chance to have a site walk as part of the public hearing. I
understand that part. Maybe I'm thinking of times when we did have a continued public hearing
only in that
that can be useful because
and again, it's a moot point if we're not going to continue the public hearing, which we probably aren't, I shouldn't speculate.
But
anyway, I
won't make that point because it's probably not going to happen. Okay.
So we'll do a site visit
this Saturday,
9AM.
Excellent.
>> Is
anybody there willing to make a motion that we accept the application?
>> I'll make a motion.
I would like to move that we access
accept
the application
of the property of the estate of William and Casey Devine,
application
number
PAndZ3Dash20
for the creation of an accessory apartment
on 84 Bearswamp Road, aka Assessors Map 34 Block 27 Lot 6.
>> Thank
you, Susan.
I'll second that. Thank you, Sky.
Any other discussion?
Hearing none, we'll take a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Leanne?
Scott?
Aye.
>> Susan?
Aye. And I vote aye as well.
The
motion passes five-zero-zero.
>> So Jim, you're gonna go over 23B
with the Yes,
I will.
232B,
I mean.
Yes.
>> I agree with Scott. Well, I guess
it's easy once you get somebody to come in and make the drawing to put a lot of that information
that's in there on it.
It would just sort of happen.
But I'm still a little
and I don't like embarrassing myself in a public meeting like this, but you know we talked about having this as built drawing after the hole gets dug in the ground. You you kind of got to have the application done
before you start digging the hole so I don't know how we get ourselves
around
that.
But if Bill's got the place staked out where he wants it, I think we can get a picture that reflects that,
reflects the septic system on there with the leach field and the reserve field in case that leach field fails. That way you've got a place to put in another leach field. Guess that's what the requirement is.
That
should put us in pretty good shape. Right. And I know Jim can point you in the direction of a couple of engineers.
There's one right in town.
>> Go ahead, Bill. It looks like you're trying to say something we didn't hear.
>> I was just going to say, now I understand
the reserve
meaning a second place for a leach field if the first one fails,
which is why obviously they do three different test pits.
We only did two test pits.
I looked at Thad King and said, We don't need a second or third one. We've got two good test pits.
And he said, Fine. You know, you paid for free. You can have a third one if you want one. And I figured I didn't need to have the man that I had hired to come and dig the test pits to dig a third one. So we didn't do it. Now I understand what you're saying and there's no problem given the fact that where the two test pits were in space.
>> Okay.
Any other discussion on
the application
that we've got here?
And
again, in conclusion of that discussion then,
I
still want to go back and thank Bill for all the hard work he did getting to this point.
To have the information we've got on the night that we accept an application,
I think
we're
heading in the right direction on what it is we should expect to get.
Think that was,
for the first scrutiny of that,
very, very thorough and well prepared.
And so
I think there should be no reason for us that we can't get to
that
public hearing
on June 15.
Thank you.
>> A
couple of comments on that. Jim, does
the town have the signs
for posting on that? No, we do not. Okay, so
>> No, I
can try and
take care of that though.
>> And
again,
we're still operating under the coronavirus
executive order,
which
if all you have to do now is send letters
to the neighbors, and I don't think you need to have a sign,
I think you'd be well served to put one up just in case there's any public interest. I don't know that there would be any, but
Jim will go through with you what the requirements are for posting and notifications
for the
public hearing. You have to notify the adjacent landowners.
>> And I saw one of the attachments
was the adjacent
landowners,
so I know you're prepared to go out and do that.
>> I did speak to Bill about that
and I am going to send him a copy of the executive
order that details what he has to do. And I believe the signs are still in order.
Extra mail is not sent by regular mail.
Pretty clear.
You have to get him a copy.
Okay.
Anything else?
>> I will find a registered engineer. I'll start tomorrow. And maybe, Jim, if you've got some suggestions.
But I will find someone, and I will do my absolute level best to have that done and in Jim's hands for transmittal to
the members of the Commission hopefully
no later than the first week in June.
And I will do that. That would be great.
>> Thank you very much.
And that completes
our item five, new business.
Bill, you're welcome to stay, welcome to go. One of the things that I probably should have mentioned right as we started tonight, the session is being recorded.
So
it's all on
video, if anybody cares to go look.
>> Can
I ask for clarification, Mr? Chairman? I'm not sure that
the public
hearing has been set, has it?
I don't know whether that takes a motion or not.
>> I don't know either. You got any insight on that for me, Linda?
You do have to set a public hearing date. Okay. And so we need a motion for a public hearing?
Yes.
Okay,
very good.
Thank you, Bill, for keeping us honest there.
Thank you for keeping me honest.
>> Anybody
care to make a motion that we hold a public hearing on June 15 at our next regularly scheduled meeting?
So moved.
Thank you, Scott.
Thank you, Any
discussion?
>> I'll note that I will take care of posting the
the sidewalk.
>> Okay. Can I just have clarification of who made the second because everybody was talking over each other?
I thought it was Susan. I made it.
Susan. Okay. Thank you.
>> Hearing no discussion, we'll vote on the motion at hand, which is to hold a public hearing on June 15 at the next regularly scheduled meeting.
Ann?
Aye.
Leanne?
Scott?
Aye.
Susan?
I vote aye as well. The motion passes five-zero-zero.
>> Thank you for your trust
that I will do what needs to be done and thank you for your confidence
And thank you all very, very, very much for these two approvals tonight.
I won't let you down. We're going build something that Andover is going to be very proud of. It's going to be very, very consistent with the 1747
historic property.
Thank you all. I'm going to
wave off. I'm going go get my dinner.
>> Thank you, Bill.
Okay.
Moving on to old business. The item of old business is
late regulations
And
both based on
the timing and a couple of other things I want to talk about and the fact that I have not had the opportunity to spend
time with Jim
making sure that both he and I have a good understanding of the lake regulations.
I want to do that before we bring that and spend valuable commission time
reviewing that. So we will pass on that tonight. I understand that that is
a high priority thing for us to get done, but
not tonight.
Moving on to item seven, administrative report from the zoning agent, Jim.
>> Out of activity, just
springtime
sheds additions,
is a
subdivision
application
coming forward
in the near future.
The gravel pit, there is some,
what I see is,
well, too material leaving the site, but I see it being sifted and such.
So I will be monitoring that
just to be maintaining
erosion control team community gaining after storms.
They do make a point to walk by on occasion.
>> So the subdivision that will be heading our way, is that the one over that we
walked for Westchester Yes. And
>> Farms Road, I guess? It's
expected to be a two lot subdivision
actually bordering,
battling the Bolton town line. So it'll be
interesting.
>> Okay.
Yeah, that was not Old Times Road. What road was that on, Jim? I can't remember.
Webster Lane. Webster
Lane.
Got it.
Thank you.
>> Jim, what was the second item you said about the gravel pit after this is next to the Extramart, I assume after material
leaving the site seems to be being shifted and we're It's just being processed.
What I see is is material being processed.
>> I thought you said something about after something happens, something else happens
in addition to the part about the material leaving the site.
Mean, I assume The CMS we measures?
The
the
in place hasn't blown out.
I'm sorry, the what is?
The SILFEST, the erosion
control measures.
Okay.
Okay, thank you.
You're welcome.
>> Moving on to the next item on the agenda, approval of meeting minutes from April 20.
I'll move to approve the minutes of April 20.
That was Leanne?
Yes.
>> Thank you, Leanne. That's it.
Thank you, Anne.
Any discussion on the minutes?
>> Just one tiny thing. I have about five windows open at this point. I think it was at the top of page seven or near the top of page seven
about the Pine Ridge Drive. There's just one spot where it's called Pinewood.
I think every other
Every other reference
has Pine Ridge.
It's just a minor thing.
Oh, I see it. Second paragraph?
Yes.
>> Okay. Yeah. I see it there too. Okay.
Very good. Any other comments on the minutes?
And I got one
also very minor comment on the attendees
and I thought we should have
Amanda listed in that group of attendees.
So if we could add her because I know I couldn't have done the meeting without her being here and I appreciate her showing up.
>> I agree. I realized I had done that today.
I'm glad I picked up on it. Okay.
>> So Linda, last time with only the minor corrections that we made, you let us vote on the minutes as amended.
Is that correct way of doing that? I've always done it that way. I'm
happy to do.
With that in mind,
we'll vote on accepting the minutes. Anne?
Aye.
Leanne?
Scott? Aye.
Susan? Aye.
>> And I vote aye as well. So the motion
to accept the minutes passes five-zero-zero.
Moving on to item nine, miscellaneous items.
Jim, you want to talk
to turn in the money back in? The acceptance of
yes.
Do we have a copy of that
memo?
>> If not, I have a copy here and I can a hard copy and I can just read it. It's not very long.
Okay.
>> So
here goes.
Good morning, Amanda. I was wondering if you could help with something. I'm trying to get an item added to the PZZ meeting.
I do not have email for Linda, our current Commission Chair.
Purpose is this,
the Board of Selectmen and the Board of Finance have asked that any available
unspent funds
be reallocated for other purposes.
Planning and zoning has a large balance in the account
8010,
legal professional.
It would be helpful if they could make a motion to relinquish
anything remaining.
I will check on any outstanding bills to be paid before actually making a transfer. So the motion could read up to current available balance of $4,375
What was that number again?
Thousand
375.
You want to make a motion?
>> Yes.
So let's make a motion and then after we have the motion, we can
discuss it.
>> Are they asking to relinquish it at the year's end or
prior to the year's end?
>> I think they're looking to
get that now.
Our year end on the June 1?
Yeah,
so
and again,
well,
we'll
discuss it. But my assumption is that as soon as we approve it, that money is going to be allocated to other things. Right. It's the legal fund? It is.
Want me to make a motion?
>> Make a You mean, sorry,
this is Leanne. You mean our year ends June 1, not July 1?
>> The fiscal year? This is Linda. It ends June 30. June 30, okay. June 30, yeah.
That's all.
>> So did you make a motion, Scott? I can't recall.
>> I make a motion to relinquish
$4,375
from the binding and zoning legal fund.
What else?
>> That would be it, but I think it should say up to the current balance of $4,000
Okay. Just in case we have any bills that need to get paid out of that money going forward. All right, so I move to relinquish for up to
$4,375
in the Planning and Zoning Legal Fund.
Is there a second?
I second.
Thank you Susan.
Any discussion?
Who sent that to you anyways Jed?
That's
from the town treasurer Barbara.
Okay.
>> And
my only concern is I know when we went through and made up the budget for this year,
we did not put any money in the budget for
the extensive legal review.
When we created the budget for this year,
and I'm getting my this year's and next year's moved up,
but the current budget,
we put
like $5,000
in it expecting that Park Branch was going to
do a complete review of all our planning and zoning regulations.
>> Right, that money is going be put back in the new year, Jed. Okay,
>> so
if that's going back in for the new year, then it doesn't make any sense for us to retain that because
I don't think we will be having
Mark do that between now and the end of June.
Correct.
Okay.
So that was my concern
about the request and it looks like we've got that
adjudicated properly.
Any other comments on that request?
Hearing none?
>> It sounds reasonable if we're going to be able to have our money we need next year. It does. Yep. I thought that was a smart thing to do.
>> So
with that in mind, call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Leanne?
>> Aye. Scott?
Aye.
Susan?
Aye. And I vote aye as well. So the motion passes five-zero-zero.
Any other miscellaneous items
to talk to tonight?
I thought that the acceptance of resignation
from
That's item 10.
Okay.
>> We'll get there in just a minute. And we also have commission open discussion coming up. So you've got a miscellaneous item that you're not thinking of right now. We've got other opportunities to
talk about that.
Hearing none, move on to Item 10.
Jim tells me that yes, in fact, we did get a resignation letter from George Knox.
And so
>> I guess at this point, we will accept his resignation and
go on from there.
Moving on to item 11, public speak.
Anybody from the public
wish to speak?
I have one Connie Dixon?
>> Yes.
This is actually Kevin Artisan,
from 927 E Street.
Hello.
Hi.
>> Jim is already aware of the application for 12 Webster Lane.
It's not an official planning and zoning application yet. Right now, they're doing wetlands.
But, during the sidewalk, there was some confusion whether it would take a subdivision or a free cut. I know this can be handled offline. I was just wondering if the commission could clarify
clarify if it was in fact a subdivision or a free cut.
And I don't expect an answer tonight. Just wanted to bring it up.
The law was worth $19.55.
>> I'd be happy to address that. Thanks, John.
Great. It was actually
the wetlands application indicated that it was a free cut,
but the engineer,
Jerry Hardisty indicated
that it was in fact a subdivision.
Okay.
So it is, I mean,
he would not,
I mean,
when plans are
submitted it will be reviewed
in its entirety, but he wouldn't go through the subdivision process if he didn't have to.
>> Okay, that may be the case, just wanted to bring it up.
>> All. That's It's the harder way to go.
Apparently
he wasn't aware of it at the time that he submitted the
wetlands application and
it's not a big deal really. Mean it's
picked up somewhere along the line.
Fair enough. That's all I have. Okay.
>> Thank you.
Moving on to Commission
open discussion.
Anybody have anything to bring up to the Commission that
>> we should talk about? Did we hear any more on the Pine Ridge Drive thing?
>> No.
I'm surprised.
I do have an issue. I'm not on the commission, but I'd
like some feedback on now
placing
materials
on the website. Does that work for folks? I
mean, the future, the idea is that all the material would be there.
Meaning any letters in
the case of
Mr. Devine,
the waiver request
that apparently
wasn't posted,
which I didn't
post, it didn't
happen. But the idea being everything is there in one place.
The
agenda is sent out and directs people's
kind of a reminder
that there's a meeting coming
and
where it is because we're not going to be doing
this forever.
Thing and but direct people to the website. Now if people want packets,
that's not a problem. Just
looking for feedback.
>> What what does everybody think? A packet or how it was tonight?
>> I really liked the way it was tonight.
I used to hate drowning in paper.
And very often when we were review we were reviewing in the past,
we didn't have all the documents that would come in the packet. They'd show up for the first time the night of the meeting.
And I appreciated
having everything available to me and having the time to go through and study it. And I felt much more prepared than I used to years ago. I think it was a very good move.
>> I think, Stu, what we're referring to is you put it instead
of having an under planning and zoning, you can have it underneath
the meeting agenda
where the meeting schedules are
in a packet with all the all the prints
and
any other information from the applicant in the same place.
It was just you can either have it under
you know planning and zoning or you can have it under planning
and zoning
in a different place.
>> My only hesitation with that I think it would be great but my hesitation is if things are coming in last minute,
then it might be hard to get the packet together.
But what works for the Board of Selectmen and Finance
is having a deadline for
submitting
materials
for the packet.
Does that make sense? Yep.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. This is Linda. I don't know if that works
for the land use commissions. I think they go by a different set of rules as far as submissions go.
Right. You can't Well deadline. And
>> it's easier for Amanda to put it in if she just throws in one piece too.
>> Something to consider for all boards. Right. Especially with our new web site coming soon she doesn't have to open up one and put put it back in right
>> I thought the way it was done today was good I just didn't know about it ahead of time so I didn't see him until the meeting but I think it is a good way to do it the way it was done on the website now.
>> So I think Leigh Ann I think oh are you done?
>> Well I was just gonna say that I could see some of the things under
the divine property there were from
earlier and then some things were just put that in but it was nice to have them all in one place
which if it was under the agenda we would have had some last month and some this month just kept them all together
>> Susan, do you have any thoughts? I guess you said you liked it. I liked it and I fully support everything Anne said. It was just so nice to have it all there and I could trace the whole history and not be missing something and having to go back
to
a previous meeting to try to find an attachment. I thought it worked very well. So
>> I
was gonna talk about the same
thing that
Jim brought up there.
I liked having all the information
for one application
in one spot, whether it was last meeting, this meeting, or going forward. I thought that was very good. And
all the other
stuff,
if it's not to do with an application,
should probably reside
in the same place that the agenda is. So if we would have had a copy of this email that
was asking to turn the money back in or George Knox's
resignation and all that stuff, supporting documents for the agenda could be with the agenda because there's no other file for them to go into.
And so it's kind of putting the packet together. It won't be as good as
the Board of Selectmen where they're getting it well in advance.
But I also was
always frustrated
when we showed up at a meeting, found out what was going on,
and that was the first time that you had a chance to look at the documents and you could not be prepared at all. So I thought this was a big improvement
over
that.
The other,
I share the comment
that we
didn't advertise
very well
what we were doing.
I know I was
hunting in different spots and I spent enough time hunting around that I eventually found everything that I was looking for. I think it will be easier in the future because I know those places to go hunt.
It may turn out that there's a better place to align all that information and we'll figure that out as we go but
I thought
as a next step it was
very
good
and I appreciate
that organization.
I was a little
thinking that it would have been nice to have had Bill's letter that talked about all the things in his packet and then everything was aligned so that you just went page by page and I
said that may be a bridge too far at this point that
that was pretty hard. I just went through copied them all off and stuck them together in the right order so I could find them. But I appreciated that. The other question I wanted to ask of the other Commission members
is
the good
side of having a packet prepared when we get back to meeting face to face
is that I didn't have to print any of it off.
What I was always doing
was I was printing the stuff off ahead of time
and then Amanda would make another packet of stuff and so we were getting, I was getting two copies of everything
and I think
it's not a tremendous financial burden
to print it off ourselves.
Although you would think that it would be nice to have the packet there. But if we're going get the packet, we're only going to get it on the night we show up. And I think that's
not when we want it. So my sense is if you want a hard copy, print it off yourself. And
that's just
part of being a good volunteer.
Anybody got any comments on that thought?
>> Is Leanne. I have just a couple.
I kind
of see what you mean, but depending on what the Commission members want to print out, I think that could really add up.
A long time ago, we used to get everything.
We might not get it until the day of the meeting, although we usually did. We used to get things
several days in advance,
and that was ideal. And then we started getting
>> We stopped getting much of anything as a hard How did it? Did you get it days in advance, Leanne?
>> Well, depending on what it was.
If there was a deadline for somebody submitting something, then we, you know, would get it in our packet.
If something could be submitted the day of the application, then no, we didn't.
>> How did the packet get to you? Was it mailed to you or did you stop No, by and pick it
was mailed. Okay. Yep. I
have never received a packet
>> in the mail since I've been on the Commission. No, it's been longer than you've been on here since this happened. Okay. And it used to be really convenient.
So I think the but that hasn't happened in a long time and I actually asked a couple of times over the years to have it done again and no one did it. And then so again, I can see depending on how many drawings and
just how many items we want to print out that it could add up. But I think you used a good term a few minutes ago about
supporting documents. I mean, today we heard that I didn't know what was out there until the meeting. So then Amanda was able to post
all the documents with the Divine application.
And then as we were talking, I was able to go in and start clicking on them. But
since this was the first month that I didn't even receive a notice of the agenda,
think
first of all, it's kind of strange in this day and age that the office has been having trouble for months sending
e mails to anybody with a Yahoo
e mail and now they're having trouble with somebody with an AOL e mail. So that's kind of inconvenient in this day and age. And also, I think there needs to be some mechanism
to let us know that there are supporting documents,
whether it's under the
on the website that Amanda just pulled up under those items
or if it's supposed to be part of the agenda.
So it's kind of a catch 22. If we're not on getting emails
because Amanda has asked us several times to forward certain things to somebody else on the commission if we see that they have a Yahoo email because the office isn't able to do it for whatever reason. So it's almost like we don't know what we don't know. So I just wanted to share my frustration about the email,
>> but it is
going to be fixed in the near future. Right, Scott?
Eric Anderson is working on a new email provider. We all know it's necessary.
So
hang in there,
and I'll keep using the Gmail account for now for you, Leanne. But I also just wanted to
make sure did everyone get the email that came from Susan on Thursday,
May 14? It said,
please see attached agenda for May's meeting.
All of the application packets can be viewed online.
This is Leanne. I did not.
>> Okay this is Anne
I did
not see it
but I got Jed's email today
and I had also gone and searched for the agenda
on the website
Now tonight,
I have because of somebody's comment, I went and looked at my spam and sure enough, there was Susan's email from the fourteenth.
So now I made a note on there and told that it was not spam so then it came into my inbox.
>> So I probably will not have a problem in the future. Okay and I need to learn that trick because mine went in the spam file as well and
all I did was move it back over to the other side and send it out to you guys. I think it came through as from Kathy.
>> Mine came through as from Kathy also, Kathy from the building department. Right and so who would know you know Sue's there and Kathy's been gone for a year.
>> And
this is Linda and I'm not getting anything from building department.
>> And mine, this is Leanne again, mine was not in my spam folder either.
>> Oh mine came from Kathy I see that yeah.
Is it Kathy on the on the header right but then
>> Susan Mowgre signed it. I'll work with Susan to change the name of her email.
There you go, Amanda.
>> And Amanda, can you
asked her to
add me. I
>> actually sent her
the commission contact list for the land use commissions and just reminded her to copy everyone so
that shouldn't be a problem going forward. Okay great thanks. And
>> I think it is important that we get an
email just to remind us that we've got a meeting coming up and
and that sort of thing. I'd
like us to continue doing that. Having to go to the website to find all the different stuff
>> okay. It's
new, it's new but it's very informative.
All the information is there. Just everybody needs to know where it will be found.
>> And somebody mentioned that some of the attachments and the documentation is fairly lengthy.
And one of the things I've been forgetting to do while we're
all blocked out of town hall there is I was going to ask for my own hard copy of the updated
zoning regulations
and subdivision regulations so I could have an updated copy because I like having a copy where I can make notes
in there on this,
you know,
when we update it next time, fix this, you know, we had to struggle with this and that sort of thing.
I for one would like a hard copy of
updated
regs and subdivision regs and I don't know
>> about that. I would like one too Jed if you could get that. Yeah,
>> I called Eric or emailed, I forgot which it was, and he dropped
off at my house a notebook with the updated
regulations.
He just asked him to give Okay, it to
>> very good. Maybe so
Susan would you like one of those too? Sure.
So maybe Jim or Amanda can go
pull the right lever to get Scott,
Susan and I
a copy of that. Ian's already taken care of.
I would like one too.
>> I
didn't see your smiling face there, Lee Ann. It just reminded me when the phone rang.
Anything else that you want to do on So we can out of discussion, Jim.
>> No, but I just want to follow-up. I think what we will do is send out
a test.
Make sure we have current email addresses. It's possible that the reason there's problem is Susan's working remotely and I know she's had a lot of problems with her computer.
I don't know if that's the issue or not, but.
It's not it's
not uncommon to have of late. We've had a lot of issues. Okay,
>> we've been working on them. I I I'm gonna speak better to that, but We had the special election ballot question on funding money for
the
IT upgrades.
And everybody agreed that that was important. So hopefully those are in progress if not
They are. In completion. Super.
>> Getting work on right now as we speak, I think. Yep.
>> And so we talked about the lake regulations and
that being an important thing.
The thing
I'm trying to understand
and
make work as smoothly as possible here right off the bat is
our process of handling applications.
All the things that we talked about tonight,
you know,
we've got a bunch of things that are headed in a good direction. Again, I was pleased with all the work
Bill submitted to us for the night when we got an application
submitted.
That's pretty nice and
we will work on raising that bar but
the process ought to be well understood and
get us all the information so that when we come to the meeting we've had a chance to review all the documents
and
we can have a good
conversation about that. So that's really where I would like all of our energies to be going forward for a little bit there.
The last
two things already mentioned,
know,
appreciated
Amanda's support and when I read the minutes from the last minute, the last meeting,
I said I don't know what meeting this was, but it sure sounded a lot better than the one I attended. And so I appreciate
Linda's work on
making that
sound so nice and having all the right information in there.
So thank you. Thank you, Linda. Thank you.
>> Go Linda.
And I also I just wanted to mention to the commission that
the new town website is literally being worked on as we speak. So all the information
is being transferred
to the new one. And we should have a live site to look at very soon,
and we can start working on all the pages and get everything set.
So
it's getting closer.
Yep.
Great.
Sounds good. Almost there. Thank you. Good.
>> Any other discussion before we move on to adjournment?
Would anybody like to make a motion that we adjourn?
I'll move to adjourn at 08:51.
Thank you, Leanne.
Thank you, Scott. All
in favor?
Aye.
>> Any opposed?
Any abstentions?
Motion passes five-zero-zero.
Thank you everybody for your help. Stay safe.
Thank you. We'll see you for the
Sight Walk this Saturday morning,
09:00.
Thanks. Thank
you. Yep. Thank you. Good night, everyone.